{
  "reference_number": "9101",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "For the most serious issue facing humanity and all life on earth we need serious action. Set legislation as fast as possible. Goals are\n too airy-fairy."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "I support taking a science-based approach to ensure our efforts to reduce emissions are as impactful as possible: we should aim for\n\n negative levels of long-lived gases, while reducing short-lived gases to sustainable levels. I support this option but by 2030 not 2050\n and only if short-lived gases are cut swiftly and drastically by 2030 before stabilising. It will be willful negligence for the government to\n\n approach this in any longer timeframe."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We must take responsibility for our own emissions, not buy our way out of a meaningful contribution to reducing GHG's. I feel very\n strongly about this. Every country needs to be part of the solution. We've already embarrassed ourselves internationally by relying on\n international credits and creative accounting with carbon sinks to meet our international commitments. We need to set a gross\n\n emissions reduction target (rather than a net one, which includes trees as carbon sink offsets). We need the Government to create\n an environment where it is not a financially viable option for, for example, Fonterra - or Greymouth Hospital - to build new coal-fired\n boilers because they are the cheapest option. I agree with the PCE who pointed out “Each tonne of emissions offset by forestry is a\n\n tonne not reduced at source. Relying too heavily on forestry could lead to continued high levels of gross emissions. Pressure to\n reduce these after 2050 could entail a more costly and disruptive transition than a deeper transition commenced earlier.”"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, exceptional circumstances should allow target to be revised eg. greater scientific understanding, however this should only allow\n\n for more stringent targets, not more lax targets."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes! Let's get moving!"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "No - emissions budgets should not be altered in response to “economic changes” as this undermines their long-term certainty.\n\nHowever, the ability to revise budgets in light of major changes in scientific understanding or international agreements should be\npermitted."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "As above."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree that the Government and the Climate Commission should take the following factors into consideration when advising on and\n\nsetting budgets: • scientific knowledge regarding climate change • technology relevant to climate change • economic\ncircumstances and the likely impact of a decision on the economy, as well as the competitiveness of particular sectors of the\neconomy • fiscal circumstances and the likely impact of the decision on taxation, public spending and public borrowing • social\n\ncircumstances and the likely impact of a decision on fuel poverty • energy policy and the likely impact of a decision"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Yes - we must learn from the mistakes of the UK's Climate Change Act and specify a strict time frame for producing a plan."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Government’s policy plans to meet emission budgets should be comprehensive, fair, cost-effective, environmentally sustainable,\nand reflect a commitment to Te Tiriti o Waitangi."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Yes - the Commission should not be a decision-making body."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "The Commission should advise the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS. It should not make decisions itself with respect to\nthe number of units available in the NZ ETS, or its implementation."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree with the following collective expertise: • climate change policy (including emissions trading) • resource economics and\n\nimpacts (including social impacts, labour markets and distribution) • te Tiriti o Waitangi, te reo me ona tikanga Māori and Māori\ninterests • climate and environmental science including mātauranga Māori • experience with addressing adaptation challenges like\n\nplanning, insurance and local government • risk management • engineering and/or infrastructure • community engagement and\ncommunications. • business competitiveness • knowledge of the public and private innovation and technology development system.\n\nI think expertise in public health is also important."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Yes. This may require a separate adaptation sub-committee within the Climate Commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I agree with the proposed functions below, but recognise that nuance is required in terms of how local councils are involved: • a\n\nnational climate change risk assessment • a national adaptation plan • regular review of progress towards implementing the national\nadaptation plan • an adaptation reporting power I also believe there needs to be a clear mandate given to local government to\n\ncompel them to mitigate GHG emissions so they can take them into account in resource consent decisions etc."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Yes"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Please be ambitious. We are running out of time. This is about intergenerational justice - we can not ignore future generations. Let's\n\nfix this mess we've created and not kick the can to future generations."
    }
  ]
}
